<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Linux | (think)]]></title>
  <link href="http://bbatsov.github.com/articles/categories/linux/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bbatsov.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-10-15T00:00:21+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://bbatsov.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bozhidar Batsov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[From Linux to OSX - 1 Year Later]]></title>
    <link href="http://bbatsov.github.com/articles/2012/09/09/from-linux-to-osx-1-year-later/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-09T22:11:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://bbatsov.github.com/articles/2012/09/09/from-linux-to-osx-1-year-later</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Prelude</h2>

<p>A little more than an year ago I wrote my rant post
<a href="http://batsov.com/articles/2011/06/11/linux-desktop-experience-killing-linux-on-the-desktop/">The Linux Desktop Experience is Killing Linux on the Desktop</a>
and for the first time in 8 years I wasn't a desktop Linux user
anymore. I spent about a month wrestling with Windows 7, but let's
face it - Windows is ill suited for professional Ruby programmers like
me (and it's ill suited for most programmers, except maybe Java &amp; .Net I
guess).</p>

<p>Anyways, it was never my intention to stick with Windows - I was just
doing my Mac due diligence. Now with 1+ year of OSX usage I'd
like to share a few things about my experience thus far with you.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>From Linux to OSX</h2>

<p>The transition was initially painful - I felt very odd dragging app
icons to the <code>Applications</code> folder to install them. To be honest I was
quite puzzled what was I supposed to do the first time I had to
install an app this way (it didn't have those helpful hints with the arrows most apps
do). The Linux distro package management is definitely infinitely
better, or at least it seems so from where I'm standing. Luckily for me most of the
tools I use are available from the third-party <a href="http://mxcl.github.com/homebrew/">homebrew</a> package
manager for OSX. It's like an extremely basic version of the mighty
Gentoo <code>portage</code>, but it generally gets the job done.</p>

<p>On a more positive note - I was impressed with the quality and
responsiveness of the OSX desktop and the fact that Emacs keybindings
are used by default in its editor toolkit (and strangely puzzled by
the lack of right control key - how is one supposed to hit <code>Control +
a</code> I dare ask?). One app in particular - <code>spotlight</code>, blew me off the
water, especially after having dealt on Linux with crappy clones like
<code>beagle</code> in the past. Spotlight can truly find just about anything,
was it's own SQL-like query language and is <strong>blazingly</strong> fast.</p>

<p>I quickly found a good terminal emulator (that would be
<a href="http://www.iterm2.com/#/section/home">iterm2</a> - it's actually the
best terminal emulator in the world IMHO) and
most of the command-line apps I used from day to day were already lying around
(after all OSX <strong>is</strong> Unix) - to my great surprise even stuff like PostgreSQL
(only on OSX Server) and <code>zsh</code> came preinstalled. Most of the other
apps I really needed had native OSX ports; the others - worthy
alternatives.</p>

<p>Having hated OpenOffice.org for many years I was very pleasantly
surprised by quality of apps like <code>Keynote</code> &amp; <code>Words</code>.</p>

<p>Being a keyboard chap preaching in the church of <code>Das Keyboard</code> I was
a bit underwhelmed by the whole multi-touch mumbo-jumbo at first, but
after a while I came to the conclusion that Apple have the only
trackpads and mice that are actually worth using (even though I still
like using the keyboard way more).</p>

<p>To sum it all up - I got up to speed fairly quickly, but it was a
bumpy ride.</p>

<p>Here's a bit more details...</p>

<h2>The things I love about OSX</h2>

<h3>The Desktop</h3>

<p>It's pretty, it's quick, it's stable. It makes KDE4 and GNOME3 look
like school projects in comparison. And did I mention that the fonts
on OSX are even prettier than the ones in Windows?</p>

<h3>The OSX flavored apps</h3>

<p><a href="http://sparrowapp.com/">Sparrow</a> is the first desktop mail client I ever liked (shame on
you Google for killing it).</p>

<p>iTerm2 is the ultimate terminal emulator. It alone warrants the
purchase of a Mac.</p>

<p>Keynote is the best presentation program I've come to use thus far.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.parallels.com/">Parallels Desktop</a> is light years ahead of VirtualBox and KVM (as far
as desktop virtualization is concerned).</p>

<p>I could go on a lot like this, but I'll stop now.</p>

<p>It's obvious that Mac users have developed a taste in extremely
refined software.</p>

<h3>Hardware compatibility</h3>

<p>If something is supposed to work with OSX - it works superbly
out-of-the-box. I've almost forgotten now the days of constant battle
with crappy hardware. Sleep &amp; Wake just work. Battery life is
exceptional (due to very advanced power management capabilities).</p>

<p>Certainly controlling all of the hardware an OS will run on helps a
lot, but we still have to acknowledge Apple's achievement.</p>

<h3>Stability</h3>

<p>One year, three Macs - only two or three system crashes. For a
developer that likes to tinker a little bit more than he should -
that's impressive.</p>

<p>That having said I had some Linux desktops that used run for more than
half an year without reboots (and the reboots were often caused by
power outages or distro/kernel updates). Linux stability on a (fairly
new) laptop? Well, that's a whole different story...</p>

<h2>The things that are OK</h2>

<h3>The default apps</h3>

<p>The apps bundled with OSX are not bad at all, but they aren't
particularly great. Still - Safari is a very good browser, Mail is a
much better desktop client than Evolution/Thunderbird, Calendar is a
good organizer (but a bit buggy when it comes down to Google Calendar
integration), Messages is so-so.</p>

<p>The bottom line is - you can go a long way with the bundled apps, but
they aren't exactly perfect. My advice - shop for alternatives (both
open-source and proprietary).</p>

<h3>Mac App Store</h3>

<p>Decent way to distribute proprietary apps, but with all the
restrictions on the app sandboxing there aren't many interesting apps
out there. Hopefully it'll get better in time. The ability to upgrade
your OSX by purchasing the new version from the App Store is very cool
(for a proprietary OS of course).</p>

<h3>Emacs</h3>

<p>The Cocoa port of Emacs is a bit immature and there are some visual
glitches here and there (try out <code>M-x linum-mode</code> for instance), but
they are forgivable. I'm also missing the deep integration Emacs had with Linux.
And who the fuck designed all the official Mac keyboards without a
right control key? I finally understood why so many Mac users where on
vim :-)</p>

<p>Btw, remapping the <code>Caps</code> to <code>Control</code> is not the answer. I do it now,
I did it on Linux as well. You simply not supposed to hit Control +
any other key with the same hand. It's disruptive to your
typing... But then again - you should probably do most of your typing
will a full sized keyboard :-)</p>

<h3>Software Development</h3>

<p>OSX doesn't nurture software development as much as Linux does, but it
comes pretty close in second place. All the tools you know and love
are available, but their installation &amp; setup is a little bit more
involved on OSX. There is a reason why the screenshots in most
programming books show OSX.</p>

<h3>System administration</h3>

<p>Definitely a step back from Linux. Programs like <code>launchctl</code> (for instance) are not
exactly fun to work with, but they do get the job done. I'd never use
an OSX box for anything more than a desktop workstation. Setting up a
sensible <code>$PATH</code> is not as trivial as it was on Linux either
(<code>/etc/paths</code> and some plist I forgotten come to mind).</p>

<h2>The things I hate</h2>

<h3>The special keys</h3>

<p>Not exactly an OSX feature, but still...</p>

<p>One year and I still hate <code>Command</code> and <code>Option</code> - option is basically <code>Alt</code>
on a strange location and Command is totally useless IMHO. I'd
probably wouldn't have hated them as much if there were room left on
the Apple keyboards (expect of course the old wired Apple keyboard) for an addition control key. Luckily for me I use an
external
<a href="http://batsov.com/articles/2008/06/16/das-keyboard/">Das Keyboard Ultimate</a>
most of the time...</p>

<p>Command and Option do have some value, I'd probably would have
appreciated it if they didn't come at the cost of my beloved right
control (which I guess only Emacs users are missing anyways).</p>

<h3>No standard all mighty package manager</h3>

<p>On Linux I had <code>aptitude</code>, <code>yum</code>, <code>portage</code> and <code>pacman</code> - all amazing at what
they do. On OSX - <code>homebrew</code> is a decent option, but it's a far cry from
the might and magic of the Linux package managers. Still, <code>homebrew</code>
is better than it's alternative, so beware!</p>

<h3>Ugly XML config files</h3>

<p>Here and there in OSX you have to write some appalling <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Property_list">XML config
files</a>. I thought I'd never see the likes of those again after I put
Java development behind me :-)</p>

<h3>XCode</h3>

<p>You need to install a giant lame IDE just to get a bunch of command
line development tools? That's one of the most annoying things I've
encountered up-to-date in OSX.</p>

<p>Yep, I know about the tools being available
<a href="http://kennethreitz.com/xcode-gcc-and-homebrew.html">separately</a> for
couple of months now, but requesting an Apple developer registration
just to get them seems a bit to much to me.</p>

<h2>Epilogue</h2>

<p>Am I happier now without Linux? Definitely! Is OSX a better OS than
Linux? Absolutely not! It does have a <strong>much</strong> better desktop
experience and since I spend most of the time on a computer
interacting with the desktop - that's a big win for me. Of course I
wouldn't mind seeing Linux achieve this level of desktop maturity and
stability.</p>

<p>Should you dump Linux and join me in <strong>darkness</strong>? How the hell should
I know? :-) I'm just sharing my two cents - if you're happy using
Linux you should <strong>definitely</strong> stick with it. Obviously I wasn't and
there weren't that many alternatives lying around.</p>

<p>Not having to deal with hardware problems and immature desktop apps is
like a breath of fresh air and it more than compensates for the few
shortcomings of OSX. Nothing compensates the lack of that right
control key on most keyboards, but after all that's not an OS problem
;-)</p>

<p>There is great vibrant hacker community gathered around OSX and it's
one of the main driving forces of the OS. There is unfortunately a lot
of corporate pressure from Apple as well, but as you already know by
now - there are never perfect things, there are always
compromises. I'd rather use a proprietary OS that stays out of my way,
than a free OS into which I bump at every turn.</p>

<p>Soon I'll blog a little bit more about the practical aspects and
implication of the migration. Cheers, mates!</p>

<p><strong>P.S. I've updated the original post a bit to reflect some of the
initial feedback I received.</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Changelog vs API diff]]></title>
    <link href="http://bbatsov.github.com/articles/2012/04/07/changelog-vs-api-diff/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-07T12:22:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://bbatsov.github.com/articles/2012/04/07/changelog-vs-api-diff</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is a guest post from my friend <a href="http://about.me/atodorov">Alexander Todorov</a>
who is a QA guru, software engineer and cloud enthusiast!</em></p>

<p><strong>Software changes fast! Open source software even faster!</strong></p>

<p>And once you start to update dependencies, libraries and frameworks it never ends...
After all the testing and validation you may have done there is no
guarantee that the software will keep working afterwards.
This is no big deal for small and medium sized projects but becomes a full-time
job for larger projects with longer life span which require constant maintenance
and enhancements. I've seen this time and time again during my work on various projects.
Even a simple <em>Drupal</em> based website pops up an update every couple of weeks.</p>

<p>OTOH back porting fixes and keeping stable APIs can be a big business. This is what
<em>Red Hat</em> is doing for their <em>Red Hat Enterprise Linux</em> distribution. Nearly all changes
are backwards compatible and and the software stack remains stable compared
to upstream <em>Fedora</em> or the more upstream projects which comprise it.</p>

<p>Let me say that I don't like to upgrade. Long ago I was using <em>Debian</em> <strong>stable</strong>
on my computer. Now I use <em>RHEL</em>. No fancy features, no bells and
whistles and more important predictable behavior wrt updates and APIs.
The same approach I take when developing software. I stay away from the latest and
greatest technology simply because it changes too often. I prefer mature frameworks and
packages which produce new versions every six months or less frequent.
This approach allows me to concentrate on writing code and getting the project done
instead of plumbing bugs introduced by the latest <em>package foo</em> version.</p>

<p>All this said I have a very careful approach to upgrades, especially if I'm
using an upstream package. I will first look at the changelog if any. Luckily
many of the mature projects provide comprehensive changelog records. This is
especially true for Perl packages. I'm looking for notices about backward
incompatible changes, API breakage, security notices, major bug fixes,
changes in behavior and the like.
When changelog is not available there's the commit log. I admit this is
not something I usually look at but it happens once in a while. I do this for projects
I'm particularly interested in or otherwise following.
Doing a content diff is another possibility which usually helps you
spot (if you look carefully) some API changes as well. I resort to this if I'm not able to find the upstream
source repository or when it is hosted on something ancient like CVS.</p>

<p>Based on all of this I decide to upgrade or not. With careful planning
of updates (which version, which moment of time) and testing I manage to
minimize the hassle of breaking my projects and spending days fixing
bugs afterwards. Instead I use the time to write some code that kicks ass
(or at least I hope so).</p>

<p>I'm curious to know what sort of information folks do prefer to have
when considering an update? Changelog vs. API diff or seething else?
I personally prefer well written Changelog and full list of fixed bugs.
Please cast your vote in the comments or visit the
<a href="http://www.surveymonkey.com/s/T7YW2MJ">survey</a>! Thank you!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Debian post installation setup & tips]]></title>
    <link href="http://bbatsov.github.com/articles/2011/07/04/debian-tips/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-04T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://bbatsov.github.com/articles/2011/07/04/debian-tips</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Prelude</h2>

<p>I've recently been using Debian a lot (mostly Debian Wheezy (aka
testing)), So I've decided to adapt my
<a href="/Linux/Fedora/2011/05/31/fedora-15-tips.html">Fedora 15 post installation setup &amp; tips</a>
article for Debian. Here are some of the common things I add to a
typical "graphical desktop" Debian installation as well as some tips
and tricks that you'll hopefully find useful. Btw, I highly recommend
you to use the <a href="http://cdimage.debian.org/cdimage/daily-builds/daily/arch-latest/amd64/iso-cd/debian-testing-amd64-netinst.iso">netinstall Debian distribution</a> - that way you'll get an
up-to-date installation immediately and you won't have to download
huge installation images.</p>

<p>This article will be of use mostly to people using Debian as a desktop
OS (with GNOME as their desktop environment) - it doesn't discuss any
server configurations.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Tweak defaults</h2>

<h4>Configure sudo</h4>

<p><code>sudo</code> gives you a way to execute single commands as the superuser. You
can also do this with <code>su -c</code>, but you have to quote the commands there,
which I don't like very much. To enable sudo for some account first
run the command:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ su -c "visudo"
</code></p>

<p>The file <code>/etc/sudoers</code> will open up in a customized vi editor. Append
somewhere to the end of the file the following line:</p>

<p><code>username ALL=(ALL) ALL</code></p>

<p>You should replace <em>username</em> with your username.</p>

<h2>apt-get + apt-cache or aptitude</h2>

<p>There are two common ways (and many others less popular or obsolete)
to manage packages on a Debian system these days - the simpler <code>apt-get</code>
+ <code>apt-cache</code> combo or the more advanced <code>aptitude</code> tool. I tend to prefer
using aptitude since it's a all-in-one solution - you could use it to both
query and install packages and has both a CLI and a curses interface.</p>

<p>It doesn't really matter whether you decided to use apt-get/apt-cache
or aptitude, but you shouldn't mix their usage - pick one and stay
with it.</p>

<h2>Install additional software</h2>

<p>I generally install Debian from the netinstall images and don't
customize very much the default package set since it's so easy to
install everything you need afterwards.</p>

<h4>Install REAL text editors</h4>

<p>gedit is ok for causal text editing, but professionals like software
engineers and system administrators will definitely need something more:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install emacs vim
</code></p>

<p>Personally I use Emacs most of the time and use vim only to edit
config files that require root access. If you need an advanced Emacs
setup my suggestion is the <a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/emacs-dev-kit">Emacs Dev Kit</a>.</p>

<h4>Install Z Shell</h4>

<p>It's no secret that I love the Z Shell - after all I
<a href="/Z%20Shell/2011/04/29/one-shell-to-rule-them-all.html">rave about it</a>
quite often. It should come as no surprise that I happen to use it and
probably you should start using it as well:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install zsh
$ sudo vim /etc/passwd
</code></p>

<p>Find the line about your account and change there <code>/bin/bash</code> to
<code>/usr/bin/zsh</code>. Alternatively you can use the chsh program to
achieve the same result:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo chsh
</code></p>

<p>Afterwards start a new login shell and a simple wizard will
fire up asking you some questions to create a default .zshrc file for
you. Alternatively you can use the excellent <a href="https://github.com/robbyrussell/oh-my-zsh">O My Zsh</a> config - I'm
very fond of it.</p>

<h4>Install guake(a drop down terminal)</h4>

<p>I spend a lot of time at the terminal and like to have one at my
fingertips always. Since I'm a GNOME user guake is the best option for
me:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install guake
</code></p>

<h4>Install LibreOffice</h4>

<p>LibreOffice is currently the best Linux option for word processing,
spreadsheet handling and presentation creation. It's generally
installed by default if you select the "Graphical Desktop" option in
the installation wizard, but you can install the
most common components at any time with the following command:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install libreoffice-calc libreoffice-impress libreoffice-draw libreoffice-writer
</code></p>

<p>LibreOffice uses hunspell to do spellchecking. An English dictionary
will be installed by default, but you'll need to install additional
dictionaries manually:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install hunspell-bg
</code></p>

<p>This command will install the Bulgarian hunspell dictionary. You
likely don't need it so install some more helpful dictionary instead. :-)</p>

<h4>Install OpenJDK</h4>

<p>If you need to run Java programs/applets:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install openjdk-6-jre
</code></p>

<p>If you're planning to do some Java development:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install openjdk-6-jdk openjdk-6-doc openjdk-6-demo openjdk-6-source
</code></p>

<h4>Install Deluge torrent client</h4>

<p>The default Transmission torrent client is pretty basic. I recommend
you to replace it with the much more feature-rich deluge:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install deluge
</code></p>

<h4>Install Inconsolata font</h4>

<p>I'm a software engineer and I obviously spend a lot of time reading
and writing source code. I'm very picking about the monospace font
that I use and currently Inconsolata happens to be my favorite:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install ttf-inconsolata
</code></p>

<h4>Install GIMP</h4>

<p>A lot of you might need an image editor. GIMP is generally
considered the best option so you might want to install it:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install gimp
</code></p>

<h2>Install additional patent encumbered/proprietary software</h2>

<h4>Enable non-free repo</h4>

<p>Just add contrib and non-free to the list of your enabled repos. Your
first line in /etc/apt/sources.list should look like this:</p>

<p><code>bash
deb http://ftp.bg.debian.org/debian/ wheezy main contrib non-free
</code></p>

<p>Then do a:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude update
</code></p>

<h4>Install proprietary codecs</h4>

<p>No MP3 support in Debian by default? And almost no video codecs?
Non-free to the rescue! Type this:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install gstreamer-plugins-ugly gstreamer-plugins-bad gstreamer-ffmpeg
</code></p>

<h4>Install VLC</h4>

<p>With MPlayer's development in stagnation VLC has established itself as
the best video player for Linux recently. Installing it is as easy as typing the following command:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install vlc
</code></p>

<h4>Install Adobe Flash Player</h4>

<p>Love it or hate it - you probably need it.</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install flashplugin-nonfree
</code></p>

<p>You can omit this if you're planning to use Google Chrome (on a 32bit system), since it
comes with Flash Player built-in.</p>

<h4>Install Skype</h4>

<p>In a perfect world everyone would be using Google Talk... In the real one:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install skype
</code></p>

<h4>Install Oracle JDK</h4>

<p>OpenJDK is great, but due to licensing problems it's not quite the
same as the Oracle JDK. If you start experiencing strange problems
(mostly in Swing programs) you'd probably do well to try the Oracle
JDK instead. The magic incantation goes like this:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install sun-java6-jdk sun-java6-demo sun-java6-source sun-java6-plugin
</code></p>

<p>Debian uses OpenJDK by default, so you'll have to do some more work to
tell it to start using Oracle JDK. The <code>alternatives</code> program allows
you to select between multiple installed versions of a program:</p>

<p>These commands will make alternative aware of the java binaries and
set high priorities to them which will make them the default Java
binaries. You can use "alternatives --config binaryname" to select
active binaries manually.</p>

<h4>Install Google Chrome</h4>

<p>Firefox is dying, Google Chrome is the new king of the
browsers. Download it from the <a href="http://www.google.com/chrome">official site</a> and install it:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo dpk -i ~/Downloads/google-chrome-stable_current_i386.deb
</code></p>

<p>Google Chrome will install a apt repository as well, so you'll receive
updates as soon as they arrive.</p>

<p>Alternatively you can use Chromium - Chrome's open source sibling:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install chromium-browser
</code></p>

<h4>Install DropBox</h4>

<p><a href="http://www.dropbox.com">DropBox</a> is a great file sharing service
which allows you to sync files between all of your computers and
mobile devices(Android, iPhone, iPad, etc). It has a great Linux
client which I use all the time. It's available in the non-free repo
so you can install it like this:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install nautilus-dropbox
</code></p>

<h2>Epilogue</h2>

<p>Hopefully some of my setup has made your setup more enjoyable and more
productive. I'll update this article along the way if I stumble upon
other things that I consider to be generally helpful.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Linux desktop experience is killing Linux on the desktop, Part II]]></title>
    <link href="http://bbatsov.github.com/articles/2011/06/14/linux-desktop-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-14T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://bbatsov.github.com/articles/2011/06/14/linux-desktop-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Read this with an open mind.</em></p>

<h2>Prelude</h2>

<p>A few days back I wrote a somewhat controversial article called,
<a href="/Linux/Windows/Rant/2011/06/11/linux-desktop-experience-killing-linux-on-the-desktop.html">"The Linux desktop experience is killing Linux on the desktop"</a>. While
many readers seem to have grasped the true purpose of the article, a
lot of people claimed that it was nothing but FUD (a favorite term
of many people in the Linux community, who would rather ignore
existing problems than face/acknowledge them).</p>

<p>If you've read my last post and generally agree with it - don't bother
reading this one. It's basically more of the same - in greater detail
and with less profanities.</p>

<p>In this article I'll have a look at the state of the Linux desktop,
it's usability, strengths and weaknesses.</p>

<h2>Let's get some facts straight</h2>

<p>I'm writing this post from my Emacs 23.2 client (in Markdown, to
publish it via git to my jekyll powered blog) connected to my Emacs
daemon, running on my Fedora 15 GNOME 3.0 desktop at home. This
machine has its every part carefully selected for maximum Linux
compatibility (the machine is a bit old, but that wasn't always the case) -
a GeForce 9600GT known to work "great" with the open-source nouveau
driver, an Asus Xonar DX sound card, supported by the great Oxygen HD
audio driver, etc. I do know how to buy hardware (contrary to popular
belief). Actually I've been a hardware
enthusiast for most of my life and I know much more about the inner
workings of computer components than most people. That said - the hardware that
I bought for my home PC was not the hardware that I wanted to buy, but
the one I had to buy.</p>

<p>Even the ill-fated T520 Sandy Bridge laptop was supposed to work very
well with Linux - after all Intel and Nvidia video cards are the
safest bet in town.</p>

<p>One of the great things about using a free (as in speech) OS like
Linux is that you get to do things exactly the way you want to do
them. You're in control. Everything is transparent. Nothing magically
happens behind the scenes. It's sad that this
doesn't extend to the ability to pick any piece of fairly generic
hardware and properly enjoy it. Often you just have to hope
and pray - and sometimes you might get lucky.</p>

<p>A reader pointed me to
<a href="http://blog.eracc.com/2011/06/14/the-century-of-the-linux-desktop/">this piece</a>
- a rebuttal of my article. Here's an excerpt:</p>

<p><em>Here we go again. Some fellow has gotten all whiny about being such a
big Linux fan, "… hardcore Linux user …", but he just had to go back
to Microsoft to get things done. Why? Because he is tired of having to
tinker with Fedora Linux to make things work, or fail to work, with
cutting edge hardware … and 64-bit Flash on 64-bit Linux is sucky …
and Skype on Linux is sucky … and … and … and. It was all just so
painful and time consuming he could not take it any longer and went
back to the safe arms of Microsoft to escape the horror that is
Linux. Good grief.
Okay, first and foremost, a true "hardcore Linux user", in my mind a
fan of Linux, is unlikely to switch from Linux to anything else. Oh
yes, he or she will switch Linux distributions in a heartbeat, or
maybe three heartbeats, if a distribution fails to work as needed. But
switching to Microsoft and leaving the Linux desktop behind? Not
likely, my friends. I consider myself a true "hardcore Linux user" and
I see no voluntary switch from Linux in my future … ever.</em></p>

<p>This bit produced a sad smile on my face. Had to go back to Microsoft?
Absolutely not! Chose to use Windows 7 (for the time
being)... If I was to go back to something it should have been FreeBSD
since it was the OS I was using before Linux (and of course Windows
before that indeed). I actually switched quite reluctantly from
FreeBSD to Linux for a simple reason - Linux supported wider hardware
variety and there were more native apps for it.</p>

<p>All Unix-derived OSes are more or less the same from an user's
perspective - mostly the same environment, the same applications. The
only thing that really makes the difference is the hardware support
and Linux is clearly far ahead of its competition.</p>

<p>Hardcore user? You bet! But hardcore doesn't mean an 'unreasonable
idiot, blinded by zealously'. It's not always that someone's favorite
technologies are the best solution to a problem. The section "the shit
I've endured" had a dual purpose - list a "few" problems and show how
resilient I am.</p>

<p>Distro hopping is something that mostly newbies do, because they fail
to grasp a fundamental thing in the land of Linux - 95% of the stuff
that comprises a distribution is generic stuff found in most other
distros. You cannot seriously expect that the same drivers in a
different distro will yield wildly different results... Sure, bugs do
tend to occur, and sometimes they are truly distribution
specific. Sure, some distros happen to patch the stuff they ship
heavily, while others favor shipping vanilla versions of both software ant
the kernel.</p>

<h2>The process of driver development</h2>

<p>My former post placed a heavy emphasis on existing driver
issues. While I abhor some Linux drivers I've never ever blamed the
authors of open source drivers. Here's why:</p>

<p>The year and a half I've spent writing Linux drivers for a proprietary
Austrian company was some of the hardest time in my professional
career. Writing drivers is fairly hard task for two reasons - you have
to have very intimate knowledge of the hardware at hand and you have
to write very safe code (and carefully test it), because otherwise you might bring the whole
kernel down. I was basically reading tech specs (most boring read in
the world) most of the day and
writing very little code in end. Debugging drivers is not a pleasant
task either.</p>

<p>Linux certainly has some of the best developers in the world. I have
little doubt in that. The problem is that these same developers spent
their days working other jobs and you cannot seriously expect them to
have the time or the energy (not to mention the specs required) to
produce drivers that are on par with commercial counterparts developed
for OSX and Windows by big team with vast resources at their disposal.</p>

<p>This is the actual problem as I see it - we're expecting individuals
to create good drivers for us out the kindness of their hearts in
their little spare time with little or no hardware specs on which to
rely for absolutely no money.</p>

<p>I've read the source code of many network layer drivers in the Linux
kernel and I've noticed a common trend - a lot of the drivers were
actually written by hardware engineers (instead of software engineers)
- they are filled with copy/paste segments from other drivers, lots of
  useless/dubious/dangerous code. This doesn't surprise me - few
  software engineers have solid grasp of hardware and/or the will to
  take part in driver development. This is a big problem with no easy solution.</p>

<p>The hardware vendors are the only party that deserves blame for the
sorry state of many drivers. I cannot believe how hard it is for a
company with the size of AMD to deliver a decent Linux driver
for so many years. Their driver is a monument of everything that is
wrong with hardware vendors as far as Linux is concerned - no support
for latest kernels/X, no support for current state-of-the-art Linux
video technologies, notorious instability and performance. Nvidia fare
a lot better but still - their driver lacks the support basic stuff
such as KMS...</p>

<p>So what can we do? Obviously not everyone can start writing better
drivers, but still everyone could try to help...</p>

<p>For most desktop hardware vendors Linux is a non-existing OS. Linux
truly has a small market share, but that is not the actual
problem. The actual problem is that Linux desktop user would rather
wait for someone from the community to come up with a solution instead
of the pressure the vendors into action. Fill their mailboxes with angry
letters, write blog posts about their inadequacy to properly support
the third largest desktop OS in the world. Companies love to make
money and hate bad press...</p>

<h2>The desktop software stack</h2>

<p>The Linux desktop stack has some great qualities - for instance it
often comes with batteries included. You have most of your day to day
need covered as soon as you install your distro - a decent browser, a
good email client, an office suit, disk burning utility, torrent
downloader, IM client, text editors, photo organizers, image editors,
etc. When I installed Windows 7 I was a bit surprised how bare the
initial installation is and how many third party apps I needed to
install. And of course most of the Linux desktop apps coming from the
same environment (KDE, GNOME, XFCE, etc) have a very uniform look and
feel to them which I personally value a lot.</p>

<p>Unfortunately not everything is great...</p>

<p>The Linux desktop application stack suffers from a few serious
problems:</p>

<ul>
<li>a few individuals make crucial decisions without taking any input
from the user community</li>
<li>many projects have only one principle developer that happens to do
things his way without regard for anyone else</li>
<li>often highly unstable beta quality software is pushed as stable to
the end users</li>
<li>a lot of prominent apps that are multi-platform seem to undergo
sub-par testing/QA process under Linux and experience common problems
like crashes and memory leaks that don't manifest that often on
other platforms</li>
</ul>


<p>In more details...</p>

<p><strong>Is it really better for the users?</strong></p>

<p>Often a new feature arrives that is marketed as a huge improvement for
the end-users. Most of the time the end-users are never inquired about
their opinion of the feature. PulseAudio is a great example. I was
pretty happy using ALSA directly, but nobody asked me what I thought
about the change. Initially it was fairly easy to disable pulse audio,
but as it became more and more integrated into the desktops the
process became harder (luckily pulse audio improved in the
process). While I'm perfectly aware of the technical reasoning that
lead to pulse audio's creation I do find it rather useless. With only
one major architecture left (almost no one uses OSS on Linux these
days) the introduction of intermediate sound layer of dubious quality
never made that much sense to me. Sure, ALSA needed a simpler API, but
we didn't deserve to be punished with pulse audio...</p>

<p><strong>It's my way or the highway</strong></p>

<p>Most of you probably remember that Pidgin (formerly Gaim) used to be
the default IM client in GNOME based distros. At some point this
quickly changed and Empathy became the default client. Part of the
reason for the switch was the unwillingness of the lead developer in the
Pidgin project to collaborate with the GNOME developers. I still
remember the controversial fix that made the input area non-resizable
with no option to go back to the previous setting. I guess GNOME's
devs were really pissed about something since they replaced the all around great
Pidgin with a vastly inferior and immensely buggy (at least for the
first year and a half) product.</p>

<p>Too much power of the hands of a single person with no overseer is
dangerous. In the open-source world one can easily fork a project, but
this is a dangerous path as well that is often likely to wreak havoc
into the development of the project.</p>

<p><strong>Are we your users or your beta testers?</strong></p>

<p>A few examples from recent years:</p>

<p>KDE 4.0</p>

<p>GNOME 3.0</p>

<p>Empathy</p>

<p>PulseAudio</p>

<p>NetworkManager</p>

<p>Beagle</p>

<p>The list could go on and on... Microsoft and Apple have certainly had
their fair share of mistakes (Win ME, Win Vista, OS X Leopard), but
nothing on a scale as epic as KDE 4.0 or GNOME 3.0...</p>

<p><strong>Some users are more important then others it seems...</strong></p>

<p>All those programs run on all major OS, but they perform worst on Linux:</p>

<p>Firefox</p>

<p>OpenOffice</p>

<p>Flash Player</p>

<p>Obviously writing great multi-platform apps is possible as illustrated
by software such as VLC and Google Chrome. But what about all the
rest. I feel that Firefox's days as the dominant browser on the Linux
desktop are numbered - most of my friends that use Linux have already
switched to Chrome (or the open source Chromium). Firefox on Linux is
like a bad joke - slow, memory hungry and unstable. I keep hearing
that it runs a lot better on OSX and Windows, probably because it got
a lot more testing on those platforms. I understand their reasoning -
most of their clients use those two OSes so it makes sense to make them
important in the dev/testing phases. But they should remember
something - Firefox is (for now) the default
browser only in most Linux distros and it's never going to be the
default in Windows or OSX...</p>

<p>Same goes for OpenOffice to the letter.</p>

<p>And flash is well -
flash. It's not the greatest piece of software on any platform, but
it's absolutely horrible in Linux. When I open a flash intensive web
site my CPU load generally spikes up to the sky (thank God for AdBlock
&amp; FlashBlock).</p>

<p>Skype was not even mentioned here (until now obviously) since the Linux version is so far behind
the one for OSX and Windows that I wouldn't even consider it a
port. It's just some pile of crap compiled to be able to list Linux as
a supported OS on their website... They promised improvements, they
promised an open-source Linux client - two years later we're still
using Skype 2.1 BETA. I wish more people had the sense to use a
service like Google Talk so I wouldn't have to put up with skype at all.</p>

<h2>The community (communist) model</h2>

<p>I live in a country from the former Soviet block (Bulgaria) and I've seen first
hand what Communism leads to. I've also seen first-hand why Communism
doesn't actually work - few people actually live and abide by it and
the rest of society simply practices the fine art of "getting by" and
lives on their shoulders. The Communism can only really work if
everyone is pulling their own weight in it (which sounds a bit absurd indeed).</p>

<p>Something similar is happening on the Linux desktop ship - everybody
says he's on board, but very few people are actually rowing and
bringing the Linux desktop to it's designated port.</p>

<p>I've written only two desktop project for Linux from scratch (an
English-Bulgarian dictionary utility and a GUI front-end for pacman on
Arch Linux), but I've contributed bug reports and patches to lots of
projects. No matter what your opinion about me is - I've done
something for the Linux desktop and I'm doing something for the desktop now
as well - writing this article...</p>

<p>What have you done? Sure, very few users are software engineers, but
that doesn't mean they can't help. Bug reports are just as important
as patches. Ideas and suggestions for improvements are highly valued
as well. Don't sit in the shadows doing nothing - step into the light
and do something to help your favorite project get a little bit
better.</p>

<p>Step by step. Fix by fix. Improvement by improvement. This is how good
software gets created.</p>

<p>The bottom line is - the more of us that pitch in the fight for a
proper Linux desktop experience, the bigger the chances of the dream
becoming reality become.</p>

<h2>Future</h2>

<p>Unless something radically changes in the near future I don't see how
Linux can rise up to be a mainstream desktop OS. With very few
companies having any stakes in the Linux desktop that isn't happening
any time soon. I find a somewhat troubling trend in recent years - a
lot of companies that worked for a better desktop experience are now
gone. Ximian (the company behind GNOME) was purchased by Novell and
later Novell crumbled, making the future of one of the most popular
desktop distributions OpenSUSE doubtful. Mandrake was once one of the
most powerful Linux companies and Mandrake Linux was widely
used. Currently Mandriva is constantly on the brink of
bankruptcy. There are many other examples - Xandros, VidaLinux,
etc... Even the "mighty" Canonical struggles to build a successful
business model around their widely successful Ubuntu OS.</p>

<p>Desktop Linux has to be made somehow profitable for companies to start
investing more heavily in it. This is the hard, but honest truth. As
long as the primarily development is carried out with little (or no
funding), mostly by volunteers the hour of the desktop Linux will
never come.</p>

<p>There is one more serious problem - diversity. There are two many
distributions bring too little value to the table. The time spent
repacking the same software for a hundred distros could be better
utilized developing new applications/drivers and improving existing
ones. We need to have at least a couple rock solid desktop
distros/environments, otherwise the whole diversity thing means
basically nothing.</p>

<p>Few good options are worth more than a million half-baked options!</p>

<h2>Epilogue</h2>

<p>This article (and the one before it) was never about jumping the
ship, claiming that Windows or OSX are better than Linux or spreading
"FUD" (if I totally hate a term this is the one). It was always about
raising the awareness of existing issues in the land of desktop
Linux. After all just a few days before <a href="/Linux/Fedora/2011/05/31/fedora-15-tips.html">I had written a post
installation guide for Fedora 15</a>.</p>

<p>While I was writing the last paragraph I got another GNOME 3 shell corruption (time
for killall gnome-shell to take the stage) on my totally supported
hardware... A skype sound notification interrupted the song I was
listening to (thanks a lot, PulseAudio)... And yet I'm still here. I
did switch to Windows 7 on my laptop and I do intend to use Window 7
at least for a while there. It's not perfect either, trust me about
that. Poor terminal emulator (though great PowerShell), a few random
application crashes (but these happen in Linux as well in recent
years) just to name a few.</p>

<p>The Linux desktop is at the edge of a cliff now. It's up to us to
decide whether we would save it or push it over the edge.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Linux desktop experience is killing Linux on the desktop]]></title>
    <link href="http://bbatsov.github.com/articles/2011/06/11/linux-desktop-experience-killing-linux-on-the-desktop/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-11T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://bbatsov.github.com/articles/2011/06/11/linux-desktop-experience-killing-linux-on-the-desktop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong></p>

<p><em>This post is a bona fide rant. It tells how a hardcore Linux user
(me) decided to abandon Linux as a desktop platform and the reasons
behind this decision. It might provoke some controversy, but
I frankly don't care.</em></p>

<h2>Prelude</h2>

<p>I'm generally known as one of the biggest supporters of GNU/Linux,
I've taught courses on Linux administration, I've spoken at Linux
conferences and I naturally use Linux as my primary desktop on all my
machines. Well, that last part is not so true anymore. Here the story
begins...</p>

<h2>The background</h2>

<p>I've been using GNU/Linux exclusively for 8 years now. I've spent a
lot of time with Fedora, Gentoo and Arch Linux. I use it at home, I
use it at work and along the way I've converted many Windows users to
Linux. I've lived through a lot of driver and software problems
with Linux, hoping that the day would come when it will become a
first-class citizen of the desktop operating systems town. Alas, this
day never came and probably never will.</p>

<p>My patience ended this week and I'll be gradually moving all my
desktop machines back to Windows. What caused me to take such drastic
course of action? I've bought myself a new ThinkPad T520 laptop,
powered by Nvidia's Optimus GPU switching technology - when the GPU
load is low it uses the built-in Sandy Bridge GPU, when it gets higher
- it switches to the discrete NVS 4200M GPU. Needless to say - this
  technology is not supported under Linux, but I was prepared to live
  without it. After all both Intel and Nvidia are known to have decent
  Linux drivers so I was about to try both GPU and select the one with
  the better performance. All I had to do was pick a shiny new
  distribution to power my mobile powerhouse...</p>

<h2>The Distribution</h2>

<p>I love Fedora - always have, always will. They constantly deliver to
the end users the cutting edge in Linux technologies (both desktop and
server), so it's naturally my distro of choice (I'm quite fond of
cutting edge tech). I installed on the new
laptop the latest Fedora 15 with GNOME 3.0 and here the problems
started. GNOME 3 requires 3d acceleration to work properly - a
reasonable requirement these days, at least on an operating system with
normal video drivers.</p>

<p>The Intel driver sucked so bad that I got constant screen corruption
and hang-ups. Too bad, because I preferred to use the Intel GPU since
I mostly work on the laptop. The open source Nvidia driver nouveau
doesn't support the NVS 4200, so I was forced to install the
proprietary driver. It ran OK initially, but after some time my system
just started to freeze while waiting for Plymouth (probably after some
kernel update, which I didn't notice). I could have tried the usual
tricks and fixed the problem, but at this point I finally realized how
idiotic it was of me to keep using Linux for a desktop OS after all
the shit I've endured and the time I've wasted dealing with stuff that
should have been "just working". I just want to get some work done, I
don't want to waste my time debugging all kind of crap.</p>

<h2>The Shit I endured</h2>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong></p>

<p><em>I've endured this Shit over the aforementioned period of 8
years. Some of the problems here have been alleviated (like
ethernet/wireless support) and some manifest mainly with newer
hardware (released in the past 6-12 months). Many of the problems,
unfortunately manifest on all kind of hardware no matter how old.</em></p>

<p><strong>Non-existing ethernet/wireless drivers</strong> - not so common today, but
  try remembering the time circa 2005</p>

<p><strong>Non-existing/crappy audio drivers</strong> - got an X-Fi 5 years ago, ALSA
  driver was released 3-4 years later and was total piece of garbage,
  OSS driver was barely usable. I don't even get me started on USB
  audio support - what a joke...</p>

<p><strong>Lamest video card drivers ever</strong> - most video card drivers for Linux
  are so bad I cannot even watch tear-free video. Nvidia have the only
  decent video driver, but it's far from perfect either - no KMS, poor
  2D acceleration. AMD's drivers are a punishment from the Lord and
  Intel's constantly "evolving" drivers are barely usable most of the
  time. The video card drivers made me buy and HD media player and an
  PS3 (for which I'm thankful), but I have to ask myself - why suffer
  all this shit instead of getting a normal desktop OS like OS X or
  Windows? Did I love Linux that much? Did I believe that much it's
  desktop day would come? What an idiot I was.</p>

<p><strong>Lack of printer drivers</strong> - that's a funny one. Often printers
  listed as having Linux drivers are mostly unusable. The printer that
  own is listed as having a "perfect" Linux compatability in
  openprinting.org. If this is perfect I cannot begin to imagine what
  is "poor" compatibility.</p>

<p><strong>Crappiest suspend/resume support</strong> - laptop goes to sleep, but
  doesn't wake up. Wireless dies after wake up. Suspend/resume used to
  be something mythical to most Linux users. Recently the situation
  has improved a bit it's still light years away from what you get
  with Windows/OSX.</p>

<p><strong>Poor power management</strong> - my older laptop's battery lasted several
  weeks while sleeping when I was using Windows on it. When I replaced
  it with Linux the battery was being drained in 2 days while the
  laptop was sleeping (and I had to wait about half a year for a set
  of wireless and video drivers that actually made sleep a
  possibility)... I've noticed that as far as dynamic power
  management is concerned Windows generally managed to squeeze more time
  out of the battery, while at the same time my rig generated less
  heat (dynamic fan control is another weakness of Linux).</p>

<p>I'll stop writing about the driver problems now, because they affect
so many thing. Even my fairly advanced mouse is missing some functions
in Linux. I'm not even mentioning the things like support for "Turbo
Memory", Optimus, etc.</p>

<p><strong>Lack of decent office software</strong> - call it OpenOffice.org and don't
  insult it anymore...</p>

<p><strong>Problematic sound architecture</strong> - let me be completely blunt -
  everything sound related in Linux sucks - OSS, ALSA, PulseAudio (the
  sucker king). From a technical standpoint OSS never actually sucked,
  but since it wasn't picked up by the community the project fell
  into oblivion. How many of you have enjoy Dolby Digital or DTS sound
  from their Linux boxes?</p>

<p><strong>Poor flash support</strong> - should I explain? Have you tried it on a 64
  bit distro? Do I hate it? Sure. Do I hope HTML5 will kill it?
  Sure. Do I need it? Sure. You think your video drivers work OK under
  Linux? Have you tried playing a HD video clip in youtube with flash
  player at full-screen? Very few Linux video drivers handle this task properly...</p>

<p><strong>Poor skype support</strong> - Same story as with flash. I keep dreaming of
  a world with more intelligent users where GTalk has a conference
  mode and everybody's using it instead of skype.</p>

<p><strong>Poor quality of desktop apps</strong> - Known issues in core applications
  such as Nautilus don't get fixed for years. Such things naturally
  piss me off. Trying to contribute to the solution of a problem is
  often met with apathy by maintainers. Btw Linux users think that
  Mozilla Firefox is very slow and memory hungry - but it turns out
  that the Windows version is generally performing a lot better (not
  to mention - supporting hardware video acceleration).</p>

<p>I can keep listing things here forever. When I come to think about it
for the entire time I've been using Linux only one major problem got
resolved - USB devices support. I still remember the days when I had
to write auto mounting policies myself or to use <em>mount</em> manually all
the time. I won't even mention the quality of most proprietary apps on
Linux, the huge amount of missing essential application and the
unavailability of mainstream video games.</p>

<p>So this is it! Hasta la vista, Linux! You still remain the best server
operating system, though. You'll always have a special place in my
heart and a VMWare instance on my Windows boxes.</p>

<h2>What I'll miss</h2>

<ul>
<li>shell</li>
<li>transparency, control</li>
<li>package management</li>
<li>lack of viruses, malware</li>
</ul>


<p>Although most common desktop users probably don't use the shell very
often, I practically live(d) in it. OS X has zsh and bash, so it's a
long term option for me, but due to the need for new hardware I'll be
using Windows 7 on the desktop front for now. Hopefully the rumors
that PowerShell is great will turned out to be true.</p>

<p>The ability to tweak every aspect of the configuration, to build
custom drivers and kernels will be missed as well, but I don't tend to
do this as often as I used to. And when something bad happens - most
of the time you could do something about it. As a friend of mine used
to say "The single biggest difference between Windows and Linux is
that in Windows the restart will solve just about any problem, but in
Linux it's unlikely so solve any problem" (this statement was much
more correct 8 years ago - modern Linux desktop distro have developed
some of Windows's old habits).</p>

<p>Probably the biggest loss for me would be the wonderful distro package
management systems like YUM and APT.</p>

<p>During the time I used Linux I totally forgot that things like viruses
and malware existed. Now, after I installed Win 7 I was immediately
encouraged to install an anti-virus program.</p>

<h2>Based on your feedback</h2>

<p>It seems a lot of people misunderstood the purpose of my rant so I'd
like to clarify something for them:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>I <strong>fuckin'</strong> love Linux. Linux is brilliant. Linux is fun. Linux
rekindled my interest in computing at a time when I was about to
give up on computing.</p></li>
<li><p>I'm not spreading FUD, I'm telling you a real story, a story that I
know many have experienced and many will experience.</p></li>
<li><p>I'm trying to raise the awareness of Linux desktop users. They've
been told that they have to be thankful for any kind of hardware
support, no matter how basic, fucked up and all around shitty it
might be. They've been told that they have to be grateful for every
crappy app in existence. The fact that something is free (as in
beer), doesn't make it wrong for people to criticize it and complain
about it. Ranting is what drives evolution. Same thing happens in
life every day - the media and the people around us proclaim
mediocrecy, they tell us that mediocrecy is OK, that we should be
satisfied by what we have and that aspiring for greatness is a
foolhardy mission. The Linux desktop community should put real
pressure on hardware and software vendors to be taken seriously,
instead of just waiting on their mercy. The Linux desktop community
deserves a great Linux desktop.</p></li>
<li><p>Fanatics are dangerous. They cannot see past their beliefs, they
cannot be reasoned with. The Linux community is full of them -
zealots that never see any problems with Linux and feel that the
entire world is on a quest to discredit their (mine) beloved
OS. They won't ever get this post, but hopefully YOU will.</p></li>
<li><p>Hardware support is a big part of the Linux desktop problem, but
it's not the only problem. Half-baked DE like KDE 4.0, Ubuntu's
Unity and GNOME 3.0 are just as dangerous.</p></li>
<li><p>Having some hardware support and having great hardware support are
two different things.</p></li>
<li><p>I do know how to research hardware compatibility ( :-) surprising,
eh?), but I do like
cutting edge technologies as well (problematic...). Does it seems
normal to you to avoid commodity hardware just on the ground that
it's "too new" to be properly employed by your OS of choice?</p></li>
<li><p>I'm not claiming that Windows 7 is the greatest thing after hot
water, I don't even say that I like it. I do, however, say that it
offers superior desktop experience (when it works, that is).</p></li>
</ul>


<p>I'll include here a great comment from Jan de Vos:</p>

<p>_While I'm still using Linux (usually Ubuntu, sometimes Fedora)
everywhere (at work and at home), I do agree with a lot of points in
this article; there are a lot of things that could be improved, and
there are a lot of frustrations that Windows users don't have. Saying so
is not FUD, it is a simple truth. If someone who clearly likes a lot of
things in Linux decides to switch to something else, that really is a
bad thing, and an indication that there are real problems.</p>

<p>In my opinion, ignoring these problems, or even denying they exist, may
be a lot more harmful than talking about them._</p>

<p>I couldn't agree more!</p>

<h2>Epilogue</h2>

<p>I remember the first time I used Linux. A friend of mine installed
Fedora 2 on my personal computer and there was a glitch in GRUB that
prevented me from booting to Windows. My ethernet card wasn't
supported so I was left without Internet. I asked my friend can I at
least watch a few movies, while he brought me a patched version of the
buggy GRUB. He told me - you need to compile MPlayer from sources with
several optimization, you need windows video codecs, etc. At the time this
excited me a lot - adventure, excitement. I learned A LOT by using
Linux non-stop for so long time. But at some point you stop learning
exciting things and are just stuck with tedious things you have to
keep doing over and over again. And as I already mentioned - I don't
want my time wasted, I want to get the job done with minimum hassle.</p>

<p>I've been hearing each and every year that "year 20xx" will be the
year of the Linux desktop. It never came and it's my firm believe that
it never will (unless something radically changes in the mindset of
Linux desktop users). Constantly plagued by hardware and software woes Linux
is doomed to fail. Without major support from hardware and software
vendors every OS is ultimately doomed to fail.</p>

<p>It's no secret that a lot of money are made by Linux server businesses
and this naturally drives a lot of the development in the area of
improving server performance. Nobody put it better than
<a href="http://apcmag.com/why_i_quit_kernel_developer_con_kolivas.htm">Con Colivas</a>
- "<em>Linux is burdened with enterprise crap that makes it run poorly on
  desktop PCs.</em>". Linux will remain the king of the
  server world, but on the desktop front it will always be an OS for
  enthusiast and hackers only.</p>

<p>Goodbye, my dear old friend. You'll be missed... but not that much.</p>

<p>P.S. Btw I'm as pro a Linux user as they get - a professional sys
admin, a former kernel developer so don't bother me with moronic
comments from the type "you're not doing something right/you should
try another distro".</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
